

Todd M. Ellis

DATA ANALYST & STATISTICAL PROGRAMMER

Greater Hobart Region, Tasmania, Australia September 2023

□+61 466 683 552 | ■ toddellis.wa@gmail.com | □ 0000-0002-4410-8676 | ■ q6vTAroAAAAJ | ■ Todd-Ellis-4 |
□ toddellis | □ tmichaelellis

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I'm a data analyst and early career researcher with a varied background in forest ecology, pyrogeography, climate change, geospatial science, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst and researcher in a variety of laboratory, field, and office settings throughout the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers in institutional policies and procedures, as well as methodological approaches to statistical analysis; and managed both complex and transformative projects for higher education, government agencies, and private industry. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, and I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

As at 2023-09-01, I have 3 peer-reviewed publications with an h-index of 2. I am the first author on 2 of these publications and have received a total of 46 or 62 citations based on Scopus and Google Scholar, respectively.

EDUCATION.

Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania

2019 - present

- · Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

Master of Science, Geography

Bellingham, WA, USA

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

2013 - 2016

- Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography and Geology

San Marcos, TX, USA

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

2007 - 2012

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Insights Analyst

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (full-time)

2023-01 - present

- Managing the development and implementation of a transformative statewide program to improve equity of access to higher education
- Leading the development of statistical models and reporting tools for managing offers and course quotas
- Streamlining and automating the higher education admissions system for school leavers
- Providing insights and consultations to institutional and external stakeholders

Adjunct Researcher

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

2019-09 - 2023-03

- · Developed complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- · Oversaw multi-year projet design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges
- Managed custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- Collaborated with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

Data Analyst

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time / full-time)

2021-02 - 2023-01

- Developed statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- $\bullet \ \ \text{Managed design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation}$
- $\bullet \ \ \text{Designed and implemented programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff}$
- Oversaw development of internal reporting and statistical packages

1	Williamson, G.J., Ellis, T.M. , and Bowman, D.M.J.S. (2022). Double-Differenced dNBR: Combining MODIS and Landsat Imagery to Map Fine-Grained Fire Mosaics in Lowland Eucalyptus Savanna in Kakadu National Park,	2 citations
	Northern Australia. <i>Fire</i> , 5(5), 160, doi:10.3390/fire5050160	
	Ellis, T.M., Bowman, D.M.J.S., Jain, P., Flannigan, M.D., and Williamson, G.J. (2022). Global increase in	
2	wildfire risk due to climate-driven declines in fuel moisture. Global Change Biology, 28(4), 1544-1559,	39 citations
	doi:10.1111/gcb.16006	
	Ellis, T.M., and Flower, A. (2017). A multicentury dendrochronological reconstruction of western spruce	
3	budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands, northeastern Washington. Canadian Journal of Forest	5 citations
	Research, 47(9), 1266-1277, doi:10.1139/cjfr-2016-0399	

CONSULTING _____

RESEARCH

2020-08 Predicting fire behaviour using historical satellite imagery
Frontier Development Lab

2019-06 Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity
USDA Forest Service

2018-08 Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth sensitivity to climate
USDA Forest Service

MANUSCRIPT REVIEWER

Climatic Change (since 2023-06)

Earth's Future (since 2022-09)

Fire Ecology (since 2019-01)

Global Change Biology (since 2022-10)

New Phytologist (since 2022-11)

HONOURS_____

GRANTS, SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

AUD\$50	Future Students Staff Excellence 2022 Sustainability Award	2022-11
A0D\$30	University of Tasmania	
AUD\$10,000	NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Prize for Applied Environmental Research	2021-10
A0D\$10,000	Australian Museum	
AUD\$1,000	Bushfire Data Quest 2020	2020-08
AUD\$1,000	Frontier Development Lab	
AUD\$28,000 p.a.	Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x)	2019-09
AUD\$20,000 p.u.	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub	
AUD\$5,000 p.a.	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3.5x)	2019-09
AUD\$3,000 p.a.	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub	

OUTREACH___

CONFERENCES AND PRESENTATIONS

2022-12	Removing Barriers and transforming access to tertiary education: The Schools Recommendation Program in Tasmania	Macquarie Park,	
	Australasian Association for Institutional Research Forum 2022	NSW	
2022-06	Dynamic mapping and analysis of fire regimes, past, present, and future	Wollongong, NSW	
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Showcase 2022 (poster)	wollongong, NSW	
2021-05	Fuel moisture trend tool	Wollongong, NSW	
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Researchers' Meeting 2021 (poster)	wolldrigdrig, NSW	
2020-03	Changes in moisture availability drive fire risk	Wollongong, NSW	
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Researchers' Meeting 2020 (presentation)		